[Music]
Bharathi I'm gonna have a dialogue
that's gonna be part of our collective
intelligence series and we've talked
about a lot of concepts on the channel
which have become quite important to
people trying to kind of follow the
thread of this conversation things like
coherent sovereignty and some people
talk about game B and definitely
collective intelligence collective
insight and I've kind of realized as
we've been doing these making these
making these films the a lot of these
concepts are things that I learn from
you we we go back about 10 years almost
now and you're kind of full disclosure
or a mentor to rebel wisdom your very
close friend and I've kind of realized
that a lot of your frameworks of looking
at the world have kind of also become
very useful and very important to me
making sense of the world and I think
they align really nicely with a lot of
what some of the interviewees on our
channel have been talking about what the
nature of coherent nature of collective
intelligence what I would say is a lot
of when I dig into these concepts
they're things that I'm familiar with
and that I know but they've kind of
gotten new names and labels recently in
this sense making conversation that's
happened so I have to kind of reflect on
it a little bit reframe it used a new
language and I just hope that I have
come away with it with a deeper
understanding and that we create a
coherent field here and that we feel
what is for me the real the most
important element of measuring coherence
or autonomy or sovereignty which is
contact and once we get into contact and
where we're communicating from a very
let's say real and honest perspective
things emerge you know some urgent
conversations happen and we can have a
little experience of some collective
intelligence right here let's do our
best okay yeah and I know you've been
following and listening to quite a few
of the other people on the channel and
what have you made of it so far
I'm really amazed at how smart some of
these people I have to say and the way
that they can articulate it and take it
apart and it's like it's sort of like
pause rewind listen again sometimes so
there's a lot of intelligence I find
some of it I have to listen quite
carefully to it but there is also
sometimes use of terms like sovereignty
and coherence as though they're like
yeah you know I just I lost my
sovereignty for a moment so I'm deaf to
go back to sovereignty or coherence and
I find those from the personal growth
aspect and the spiritual development
work that I've done to be very
sophisticated states in which I spent a
lot of time kind of not working on
explicitly on autonomy but autonomy
let's say coming at becoming an outcome
of a lot of other work of digesting and
metabolizing my own personal history
beliefs concepts the the cultural stuff
that was put into me that I just take as
Road truth when I'm young and trusting
and as I grow up and so living in my
life and start finding that I'm running
into walls then insert the question
things and so I guess what I would say
in general about a lot of it is that the
cerebral part is really great and I'm so
blessed I think and that you are able to
have these sophisticated conversations
with these people but the actual work is
a lot deeper than just sitting around in
understanding a concept because we do
have a shadow and we do have a big
unconscious and we have a lot of
repressed material we've been extremely
influenced by the culture that we grew
up in by the parental Society of the
parental influence and the personality
that we developed which in my way of
looking at things is kind of a psycho
spiritual lens is not the truth of who
we are but to get to the truth of who we
are
have to start with where I am and where
I am is locked into this personality
which behaves in a very conditioned way
and I have to be very curious about it
and after you're very willing to share
the truth as it comes up in me with
other people so that it it kind of gets
metabolized as it becomes more conscious
and then those terms oh this is a moment
where I would be usually that say
completely influenced by somebody else's
presence and actually I'm not I'm still
sitting here with myself
and I noticed a certain kind of autonomy
then you know but it's a process and so
the day only danger I think is exposing
people to really high level ideas and
then people think you know I understand
sovereignty um you know it's unto
yourself and to me when I really think
of sovereignty at which I usually use
the word autonomy rather than saw
sovereignty but I see them as very
closely related autonomy it gives a
little bit rounder and sovereign she
feels a little bit more vertical and
hierarchical maybe it because it's
related to like sovereign beings like
Kings and stuff like this but the the
thing that comes out of autonomy is
really real human contact and I feel
like more than even like spiritual
enlightenment I'm really craving and
going for real human contact in my life
and that in itself turns out to be
spiritual and I find myself transforming
in that so I'm not much on transcendence
I find transcendence has a subtle level
of rejection and it may be on an overt
level I'm more into like having the
truth and going into the uncomfortable
places and talking to people that are
good friends of mine
and baring our souls a little bit and
grinding it out I like it there's two
things that came up one was reminded
that a phrase that I've heard you use a
few times before about the personality
but you've got this sort of dialogue
between what I call the essence and the
personality that you're familiar with
from any kind of spiritual traditions
like if you look deep enough inside
you'll find the essence and there's
various maps that talk about that and
but I've heard you say before that your
personality is not wrong or your ego is
not wrong it's an intelligent strategy
to survive in the environment in your
life in so it's not wrong it's just out
of date which i think is sorry that I
said your best line but I'm just
impressed that you remembered it
precisely yeah but what I love about
that is that there's no rejection in
that because because the only way to
transform is to accept and the paradox
of that is that if we're trying to
change ourselves we won't be able to
change ourselves it only comes through
integrating and accepting these parts of
ourselves right so when I do my work I
really I make that pronouncement new for
me do it a number of times to a group
that this is a place where you're not
going to be judged
you know you've fixated in a personality
and that was a confluence of many
different elements from your parental
your school your any traumas that you
went through whatever and you survived
but you fixated into something that's
basically designed to avoid danger and
damage and further trauma in that
environment and then we take that as who
we are and that becomes what we call our
ego or personality structures that I
that we relate to and then we find that
it's very limited in terms of its
functionality it's fine if you just keep
living in the same box but if you have
this kind of urge and desire for more
you have to start taking that apart and
the only way that I see that's effective
for that is to not be judgmental towards
any person wherever they find themselves
and I find that very easy
to do an endo pointer okay that was an
intelligent thing to believe him when
you were a kid but is it really serve
you right now and then we enter into an
inquiry process and we bore down into it
a little bit and people start to as you
become aware you start to have choice
and before you're aware we're on
automatic pilot more and more robotic
and we'll just do things and we fill the
space with you know automatic behavior
yeah I want to go back as well to what
you talked about with sovereignty and
the danger was thinking that sovereignty
is something simple that we can oh I was
at my sovereignty and that you can maybe
learn it or just even by understanding
the concept that can make some
significant difference no sovereignty is
all of that it is going to be linked to
all of our childhood stuff all of our
conditioning from society and from
family and it's a huge huge piece it's a
lifetime's work just in itself I guess I
think so and I see it that way and it's
not like you suddenly arrive there and
it's done I think you can become more
and more sovereign or autonomous as new
influences come into your field and
challenge any old concepts or beliefs
it's basically not being bound by old
concepts and beliefs that came from
anything external to you so it's a very
self-realized place where you sit and
relax confidence with yourself that you
have inside of yourself what it takes to
respond to anything that comes from the
outside that's sovereign but when I find
myself losing my sovereignty when I find
myself losing my grounding when I find
myself in a contraction because I'm
somewhere comparing myself to somebody
else or somebody has criticized me or
something the way to deal with it is to
be really really curious about myself
and then with that curiosity and the
process of inquiry going into and just
bringing it up raising it up to the
surface whoa oh there's an old piece I
never looked at before there's an old
concept and somehow it gets metabolized
when it gets brought
responsibly and also yeah sovereignty
and and it can be very easily I think
mistaken for yeah Armel I'm sovereign
man are you really yeah and I wanted to
kind of bring something in as well I've
had that experience like becoming
curious of what what's coming up or any
negative reactions or any kind of
emotional reactions is something so I I
went through a period of doing a lot of
transformational workshops some of them
I did with you some of them are done
with various different kind of
facilitators and what I found after a
while was and I've used this phrase on
our workshops like becoming a detective
of our own experience and following the
thread of something would come up so if
you're on a two or three day workshop
maybe someone will say something that
sparks a thought or you'll have an
experience where you'll that will simmer
for like a couple of days and becoming
like becoming enjoying that when you
feel like oh I'm feeling angry about
something I'm feeling touched by
something getting excited about that as
a as a feeling of oh wow I'm ready to
realize something about myself and then
following the thread and almost
unraveling the thread of that experience
and finding that it almost always
emerges into some kind of realization oh
it was that experience that was that was
coming up or was that relationship that
I'm ready to look at in a new way and I
guess people who are not so familiar
with kind of the idea of workshops I
mean at a four or five day maybe even a
two day process which we've just got a
chance to play with different parts of
ourselves be more honest but we normally
would be and yeah it's sort of a much
more open space to to kind of explore
what's going on what what do you make of
that that sort of sense of becoming a
detective of our own experience I think
that that's a wonderful phrase and I'm
going to steal and start using it in my
groups because I think that the the
basis of inquiry and is curiosity and
inquiry I want to break down the word
inquiry for a moment because I think
it's such an important method of self
discovery inquiry literally mean
to question and the question means I
don't know and to not know brings us out
of the kind of certainty of our
personality structure and that lens that
we wear so we become in a kind of
liminal space of not knowing them and we
come available to truth and if we can
get excited about that if we can add
that element of inquiry and I'm really
curious what's gonna happen if I follow
this thread even it feels really
uncomfortable right now or I got really
defensive last night but I'm curious
about why did I get really defensive and
I stay with it I really trust that there
is has been known in humanistic
psychology for a long time there's this
optimising force for self-realization
inside all of us and if we get aligned
with that and we support that it is
gonna bring up what we need to know yeah
and one of the other things that's
talked about by a lot of people is the
idea of coherence and I guess collective
intelligence collective insight is sort
of based around that coherence but one
of the mistakes I think a lot I see a
lot of people making and this is
something Jaime will mentioned to me the
other day and I'd like to record
something with him about it is this sort
of idea that oh we can just go into
coherence let's let's kind of really try
and go into coherence and that doesn't
work coherence is is from what I
understand and what I've experienced
it's an it's what we it's the space we
get to on the other side of the
difficult conversations or the work or
the kind of once we've gone through
whatever is coming up that's keeping us
out of coherence then we can arrive in
that space
we can't shortcut there like it's a kind
of emergent outcome of having done the
work deeply enough to be in that kind of
coherent space with each other do you
agree with that totally I mean I think
it's another one of those kind of catch
words right now that can have a very
simplistic understanding but I see it as
an outcome and it's a it's and the
interesting thing about coherence is
like I'm Co here I can become Co here
with myself by telling the truth I can
become coherent with a group of people
by everybody is sharing their truth and
we come to a certain kind of
appreciation and single-mindedness
source whatever you want to call it a
level of contact with each other but
we're not the same and there's there is
a kind of coherence where everybody
listens to a piece of music and maybe
they become coherent you know on a
wavelength level that can be measured by
heart math or something like that but
the coherence that I'm thinking of in a
more active group is everybody is in
into their in their truth and they're
sitting in their truth as individuals
and out of that comes a space that is
very tangible that I that is that's
exciting also because we're on the edge
of something we're in contact every it
doesn't mean we're in agreement doesn't
mean we're saying the same thing but
everybody's opened themselves up and so
I think that the real doorway to
coherence is telling the truth and being
honest yeah and that kind of goes in and
out as well like it's speaking the truth
but it's also being alive to what's
emerging in ourselves and wanting to be
known because I'd say if anything as
fueled the growth of rebel wisdom so far
in its it's the it's that we've tried to
live out those values like I kind of
we've internalized those values over a
long time with being in kind of
workshops together and seeing the effect
of that speaking the truth how it kind
of creates more flow and creates more
contact and more connection is trying to
live that out in our in our interactions
with each other knowing if something's
coming up which is a practice I do with
Allie all the time at Allie also trained
with you quite a bit and that whenever
something is kind of coming up for each
of us we try and clear it and we try and
keep the field as clean as possible
between us the field the concept of the
field I think there's something I'd like
to go into as well because I think
that's really useful but I think that if
anything hos yeah I think that hopefully
is kind of coming across in the in the
work that we're doing and in the energy
of the the
that we're putting out from the kind of
courses to the to the videos to it is
that that we're trying to live out and
do the work that we're kind of making
the films about as well yeah and I think
you wouldn't be having the success and
the following of people if that wasn't
coming across if you were just working
with abstract ideas and it was just
another headspace to behold but the fact
that you guys actually share and it gets
personal and it's embodied and you walk
the talk in your life gives you some
gravitas that makes the whole thing go a
bit deeper and I wanted to say as well
like I think you have a very direct an
intuitive grasp of where we need to go
in terms of like where the culture is
and what it's missing because I've heard
you sort of say this before it's like if
we just keep going there from from here
and we see that playing out in so many
areas from politics to business to like
this it's just heady
intellectual and it's sort of playing
out what's the deeper layer that you've
experienced that you think is missing in
the world well it touches a lot of
points what you're saying right now but
one place I would go to it is the
difference between connection and
contact connection can happen very very
easily and it can be we can feel
connected because we belong the same
political party or we endorse the same
ideas etc etc and we feel connected and
it's a nice feelings better than feeling
disconnected we could cause those
friends etc but you don't really come
into the dimension of real contact until
you really like kind of naked with the
truth with another person and that's
what I think needs to happen so we have
to get out of hiding behind the
polarizations and identifications that
we have in politics and so only when
you're we really start telling the truth
that really the solutions that can come
through are greater than the sum of the
parts because I think we have the
possibility of tremendous intelligence
and wisdom arising from us but we have
to go to a place inside of ourselves
where it can come forth and so far what
we mostly have
it's just you know I've been waiting for
the synthesis to happen for so long you
know there's thesis antithesis and
supposedly synthesis is going to come
out of it it just doesn't happen it's
like the polarities just gets stronger
and more entrenched in their ideologies
and just stuck you know and so I'm
hoping that some of the work that you're
doing and some of the thinking that a
lot of these people are doing and what
we're doing in in the group space where
we're really honoring people to open up
in the way that they do can give birth
to a collective intelligence that will
start to come forth with new ideas that
will attract other people and people
will come together to live and with
different values and change can happen
because and right now I feel it's you
know it's really time for some change
and I want to talk a little bit about
the men's work because you've been very
kindly mentoring us and the men's work
we've been doing retreats for a couple
of years that started various kind of
separately from the media channel as a
sort of separate strand of a rebel
wisdom I've got a couple of questions I
mean the first one is why do you think
what do you think is necessary but what
is men's what's required from men's work
now and is any different from when you
were growing up I mean we're currently
in a kind of very interesting
conversation that's happening around
gender which makes it a little bit more
delicate but in essence I think it's the
same you know and I I think because I
still I lead these groups called essence
of masculine and feminine and I start
off and I put it in a little bit of
historical context I talk about the
women's movement and how much it
affected me and what I went through
during that time and then I talk about
what I see happening right now in the
gender world and then I say but and I
going to use a very binary language
model to teach what I think is really
important here but my vision is is
bigger and broader than that but then in
that binary one is really to look at and
see if we can bring a state and find the
state of relaxed confidence for a man as
a man and the state of relaxed
confidence for a woman in her feminine
let's say you know and then being home
there yes some people might be wondering
what does that even mean what does it
mean to be at home in your male side and
how would what would it mean not to be
at home there and how would you get to
be at home well what it would mean to
not be there would be that I would I
would not be grounded I would be in my
mind I would be compensating for a
feeling of deficiency as a man I would
have received a wound not literally
castration but figuratively and
energetically I would be castrated I'll
be cut off from my male essence and I
would be probably stuck in a kind of
boyish mentality which was out trying to
please and damage control the
environment is particularly women in
order that nothing bad would happen
which almost always ensures that
something bad will happen because I
don't know anything that women hate more
than men who act like boys so it's
getting a man to deal with his own
personal issues and I find in men's work
you know men can come to that place
where they feel something that they can
definitely identify as this is my
masculine essence I can feel it and I
can feel it in you I can feel it in me I
and I love it and they have to go
through a bit of a process to get
through that the same on the feminine
side feminine the wound is not
castration but you could use the word
castration but it's more devaluation and
feel the feminine has been devalued for
really really a long time
and so women out of their intelligence a
lot of times and because of the
devaluation to the feminine just became
better men than the men and their
masculine side took over and it's become
something called animus possession and
they're you know faster smarter quicker
better than any guy and going to the
healing of the loss of value in the
feminine is a very beautiful journey and
I love to be as a man I love to be able
to hold this male space be grounded in
this male space and be able to work with
women and help them move into allowing
themselves to feel comfortable with
their own femininity and express it
however it wants to come across you know
and and then the conversation that can
happen between men and women so in the
last few months that there's certainly
been a sort of trajectory on the inquiry
that we've been on as the channel and
also this sense of a lot of people on a
similar inquiry John Vevey key I'm
thinking of in particular focused a lot
on what is wisdom how how does that fit
together with like cognitive science and
he's now honing in a lot on what you
might call into subjective dialogue the
sort of because he sees the what we've
lost from the sort of Greek philosophers
we've kept a lot of kind of the ideas
but what we've lost is because actually
philosophy for them as a process of
discovering the truth together and that
there's lots of words for it into
subjective dialogue some people have
called it we spacers you've been doing
these practices and teaching these
practices for like 40 odd years what do
you think is really what what's so
useful about them and what do you think
of the key ingredients that we need to
do them I think that that self-discovery
process is something that has some key
components to it that can be taught and
it takes a little bit of time to get it
and one I spoke about already is
curiosity
it takes courage damn those kinds of
conversations so you might have to work
through your issues around curiosity
your issues around courage it takes a
love of the truth it takes a certain
self compassion for the way that you've
been raised in the fixation of your
personality and it takes that and it
takes curiosity as I would say with the
five main elements that have to be
active inside of somebody to be really
able to raise take questions and have a
generative conversation with another
person I think and I always have to you
know because I live in a in a kind of
small world in a certain way but I have
the sense that more and more people are
taking on these kind of questions and
willing to look and questioning and it's
all part of that what's called
sense-making crisis and a lot of people
like really looking at themselves and my
hope is is that millions of people will
start doing that and in and I think it
happens in a way in direct relationship
to the breakdown of the status quo
structure that supports the old
structure and it's good enough and we
just get by so we do need a little bit
of calamity and disturbance on the side
to kind of wake ourselves up and I I do
see that happening right now
I think the rebel wisdom is a great it's
just timely so there's lots of things
that we could have talked about I know
that we could have yeah that there's
many more hours and I hope that we this
is the first of many and we'll kind of
dig into some of these other topics over
the next year or so but thank you raffia
and you're gonna get a beer thank you -
that's
go get a beer rebel wisdom is a new
sense making platform bringing together
the most rebellious and inspiring
thinkers from around the world if you're
enjoying our content then you can help
us make more by becoming a subscriber
which will give you access to a load of
exclusive films also you can then join
our group zoom cause to discuss the
ideas in the films and you can send us
ideas for questions for upcoming
interviews and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talk a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talk about
that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon